Martin Tracey

[linkedin.com/in/marttracey] . [matracey] . [matracey@outlook.ie] . [+1-206-591-9874]

I began exploring technology playing games on my family's computer, and my passion has evolved to include programming languages, web design, networking and cloud computing. I possess a unique skill set including technical expertise, program management, business analysis, and client engagement. I'm passionate about designing customer- focused products that meet business and end-user needs. Beyond work, I'm an avid gamer and enjoy exploring how technology can improve lives, including healthcare and education. My curiosity drives me to learn new skills and explore technology's endless possibilities.

Experience

Software Engineer, Supply Chain Engineering (SCE), Microsoft

August 2019 - March 2023 Seattle, WA

- End-to-end ownership of the design and implementation of Product Costing SKU Approval and Pricing Engine processes, resulting in scalable and resilient solutions that streamlined cost management, optimized pricing strategies, and increased overall business efficiency.
- Established and maintained strong front-end development expertise within the team, providing guidance on best practices, design reviews, and mentoring opportunities that boosted team productivity and software quality.
- Led the migration to submodule repositories for Source codebase, driving clarity and productivity for Product Sourcing and Responsible Sourcing teams, reducing code conflicts and enabling faster feature development.
- Improved automated test code coverage by 8% using GitHub Copilot, showcasing curiosity and the ability to adapt to new technologies, leading to better product quality and reduced risk of regressions.
- Successfully upgraded SourceVNext codebase to Bootstrap 5, ensuring adherence to component governance and providing access to the latest features and support, enhancing the user experience and meeting security and accessibility standards.
- Delivered robust and scalable solutions for Product Costing Pricing Engine, navigating challenging development cycles and promoting a
 culture of continuous feedback and collaboration, which directly contributed to more accurate and efficient pricing decisions.
- Championed engineering excellence within the team by focusing on component governance, security vulnerabilities, and accessibility improvements, leading to a more secure and inclusive product, and fostering a proactive approach to addressing potential issues.

Software Engineer, Supply Chain Engineering (SCE), Microsoft

July 2018 - August 2019 Dublin, IE

- Successfully transitioned from a PM role to a full-time SWE, showcasing adaptability and effective knowledge transfer in a fast-paced environment.
- Demonstrated expertise in React, Redux, Microsoft Fluent UI, Formik, TypeScript, ESLint, .NET Core 3, C#, and mxGraph, leveraging these technologies to develop high-quality web applications.
- · Applied expertise in JavaScript and React to improve codebase quality, analyze unit testing frameworks, and enhance test automation.
- Drove design discussions and provided guidance on UI/UX development, including the implementation of a draggable flowchart interface using React component wrappers around the mxGraph library.
- Collaborated with cross-functional teams across time zones, demonstrating strong communication and teamwork skills in delivering new
 capabilities and functionality.
- Improved repair documentation for Microsoft's devices hardware business, leading to increased repair efficiency, cost savings, and reduced
 waste.
- Provided mentorship and guidance on UI best practices to team members with primarily backend development backgrounds, fostering a collaborative and supportive work environment.
- Overcame challenges in implementing React components that wrapped around the mxGraph library, showcasing problem-solving abilities and the capacity to adapt to industry standard design principles for components.
- Recognized for strong technical skills, effective communication, and ability to work remotely while consistently meeting project deadlines
 and quality standards.

Program Manager, Supply Chain Engineering (SCE), Microsoft

June 2015 - December 2017 Dublin, IE

- Delivered supply chain product roadmaps with a focus on UI/UX design and project management, leading to improved supply chain efficiencies, cost savings, and alignment with Microsoft's business strategy.
- Modernized EMEA and APOC sales models and organizational processes using technical skills in front-end development, resulting in optimized costs of goods sold and enhanced customer satisfaction.
- Successfully led StorSimple enterprise product enhancements by leveraging project management and collaboration skills, contributing to business growth, improved NSAT scores, and customer retention.
- · Coordinated and executed physical empty-box testing for Xbox Design Lab EU launch, ensuring timely and accurate delivery of customized

- products, driving consumer satisfaction, increased revenue, and brand loyalty.
- Managed the launch of a modernized Channel Partner Portal, leveraging my UI/UX design expertise, leading to increased revenue, improved partner satisfaction, and enhanced visibility into partner performance for Microsoft.

Service Engineer, Business Group IT (BGIT), Microsoft

July 2014 - June 2015 Dublin, IE

- Designed and maintained business services for development teams using strong UI/UX design and project management skills, resulting in streamlined service delivery and enhanced productivity across Microsoft.
- Provisioned local and geo-redundant hot-standby Perforce and Source Depot servers using advanced infrastructure management skills, ensuring business continuity, instant disaster recovery with 0% data loss, and minimized service downtime risk.
- Developed Configuration Management DB and Operations Service using strong backend development skills, enabling centralized logging, alerting, and script execution for improved visibility and operational efficiency.
- Collaborated with studio engineering teams on Perforce Service change management, proactively identifying and mitigating risks to minimize service incidents by leveraging strong communication and problem-solving skills.

Developer and Junior System Architect, MindUnit Ltd

June 2013 - June 2014 Dublin, IE

- Delivered market-leading web experiences for clients in the cultural sector, driving customer engagement and conversion rates.
- Led architecture redesign, migrating to AWS cloud services, achieving ~30% cost reduction, sustainable scalability, and enhanced reliability.
- Deployed and maintained virtual server instances, improving website performance and minimizing downtime.
- Developed best practices for security, sustainability, and performance, increasing efficiency and reducing service incidents.

Skills

frontend devops backend cloud architecture project management system architecture & design scrum

Frontend: TypeScript, Angular, React, Redux, SCSS, Bootstrap, Playwright, NPM, RxJS

Backend: C#, RESTful APIs, OData, Entity Framework, MSAL, OAuth

Cloud Architecture: Azure Web App, Azure Functions, Azure Service Bus, Azure KeyVault, Azure SQL

DevOps: Git, PowerShell, Azure ARM, Azure Bicep, Azure Pipelines, Azure DevOps

Education and Awards

BSc in Business Information Systems, National College of Ireland

- InverCloud Award for Best Final Project in BSc Business Information Systems
- Participation & Innovation Award, 2013.

Volunteer Work

Webmas: A Charity Web Development Hackathon

Annually volunteered as a group mentor in a 24-hour hackathon that aims to help students in NCI develop their coding skills by building
websites for Charitable organizations.